A Finding Aid to the Jan Van der Marck Papers, 1942-2010, in the Archives of American Art AAA.vandjan
Archives of American Art
Jan Van der Marck papers
1942-2010
AAA.vandjan
Archives of American Art
9 Linear feet
The papers or curator and arts administrator Jan Van der Marck measure 9.0 linear feet and date from 1944 to 2010. His career is documented through biographical material, files on artists and art historians, museum administration records, and other professional records. Also found are papers concerning Van der Marck's personal interest and research on modern bookbinding.
Van der Marck, Jan, 1929-2010
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The papers were donated in 2011 by Sheila Van der Marck, Jan Van der Marck's widow.
Scope and Contents note
The papers or curator and arts administrator Jan Van der Marck measure 9.0 linear feet and date from 1944 to 2010. His career is documented through biographical material, files on artists and art historians, museum administration records, and other professional records. Also found are papers concerning Van der Marck's personal interest and research on modern bookbinding.
Biographical material includes records of Van der Marck's personal collection of artwork, books, and photographs; early records consisting primarily of school documents, writings, and photographs; and one journal. Additionally there are copies of published interviews, one file of letters from friends, and several photographs of Van der Marck. Files on artists and art historians may include correspondence, photographs, slides, news clippings, exhibition catalogs, lists of artworks, exhibition planning documents, as well as articles or other writings by Van der Marck about the artist. Of note are files on Arman, Robert Indiana, Christo, Jacques Lipchitz, George Segal, Beverly Pepper, and Brian O’Doherty.
Museum Administration records document Van der Marck’s activities as director or curator at various museums. Files may include museum exhibition planning records, administrative records, printed material, correspondence, and photographs. Also found are records of Van der Marck’s other professional activities, such as his participation as guest curator of exhibitions, committee participant, and exhibition juror, as well as lecture files containing invitations, press materials, and drafts of his lectures. Additionally there are a few research files and copies of his published articles.
Papers concerning bookbinding document Van der Marck’s research and personal collection of contemporary bookbinding and book arts. Included are files on bookbinders, slides and photographs of bindings, correspondence with libraries, and records of his purchase or donation of these works.
Biographical/Historical note
Jan Van der Marck (1929-2010) was a curator and museum administrator in Detroit, Mich., Chicago, Ill., and Miami, Fla.
Van der Marck was born in Roermond, the Netherlands, in 1929. His family owned a printing and publishing business. He studied art history at the University of Nijmegen and earned his doctorate in 1956 with a dissertation on 19th-century Belgian book illustration. In 1957 he came to the United States on a grant from the Rockefeller Foundation to research the relationship between museums and their audiences and studied briefly at Columbia University. In 1962 he was assistant director of fine arts exhibitions at the Seattle World’s Fair. Van der Marck became curator at the Walker Art Center in 1963 and became the founding director of the Museum of Contemporary Art in Chicago in 1967. While in Chicago he invited Christo and Jeanne-Claude to wrap the museum building in canvas. He later served as project manager for their “Valley Curtain” project in 1971 and 1972.
After leaving the Museum of Contemporary Art, Van der Marck worked briefly at the University of Washington in Seattle, and then served as director of the Dartmouth College Galleries and Collections from 1974 to 1980. At Dartmouth he continued to support non-traditional artworks and oversaw the installation of the lawn sculpture “X-Delta” by Mark di Suvero, despite negative campus reactions. In 1980 he became the director of the new Center for the Fine Arts in Miami. After a disagreement with trustees he left the Center and became chief curator at the Detroit Institute of Arts in 1986. In 1995 he lost his job at the Detroit Institute when it was ruled that he violated a city residential requirement.
Aside from his work as an arts administrator, Van der Marck wrote and published many catalog essays, articles, and monographs on artists, lectured on contemporary art, and participated in arts organizations. He also maintained an interest in contemporary bookbinding.
Existence and Location of Copies note
Some of the sound recordings in this collection have been copied for research access and are available in the Archives of American Art offices.
Arman,1928-; Christo, 1935-; Indiana, Robert, 1928-; Lipchitz, Jacques, 1891-1973; O'Doherty, Brian; Pepper, Beverly; Segal, George, 1924-2000; Arts administrators -- United States; Bookbinding; Curators--United States; Interviews; Journals (accounts); Photographs
- Biographical Material, 1946-2009; Series 1; 0.7 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical material includes records of Van der Marck's donations of books and art from his personal collection to museums and libraries, as well as records of his photographic prints collection. These donation files include lists of items, correspondence with museums and libraries, financial documents, agreements, and related printed material. Also found are files designated by Van der Marck as "Early Records" consisting primarily of school documents, writings, and photographs. One journal is from the same period. All of these early records are in Dutch. Additionally there are copies of published interviews with Van der Marck, one file of letters from friends, and several photographs of him and his home in Seattle, Washington. Researchers should note that many additional photographs of Van der Marck and letters from colleagues and friends are found elsewhere within his papers.
  - Art and Books Donated to Museums and Libraries, 1967-2009 (Box 1, Folder 1-7)
  - Dissertation Records, circa 1956 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
  - Early Records (Pre-professional), 1946-1963 (Box 1, Folder 10-15)
  - Journal, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Letters, 1976-2006 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Photographic Prints Collection, circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Photographs of Jan Van der Marck, 1961-1970 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Photographs of Seattle Home, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Published Interviews, 1969-2000 (Box 1, Folder 21-22)
- Files on Artists and Art Historians, 1942-2010; Series 2; 4.7 Linear feet Boxes 1-6
  Existence and Location of Copies note
  One sound recording found within the files on Arman has been digitized for research access.
  Files on artists and art historians were maintained by Van der Marck throughout his career. Files may include correspondence, photographs, slides, news clippings, exhibition catalogs, lists of artworks, exhibition planning documents, as well as articles or other writings by Van der Marck about the artist. Some files are extensive and notable for their content, such as the files on the artists Arman, Robert Indiana, Christo, Jacques Lipchitz, George Segal, Beverly Pepper, and international artists such as Brian O’Doherty, Enrico Baj, Lucio Pozzi, and Bernar Venet.
  One sound disc found within the Arman files contains an audio announcement in French, created by Arman for his exhibition at Galerie Lawrence in Paris, France.
  - Albright, Ivan, 1944-1997 (Box 1, Folder 23-25)
  - Alchinsky, Pierre, 1965-2007 (Box 1, Folder 26-28)
  - Antonakos, Stephen, circa 1975-1989 (Box 1, Folder 29-31)
  - Andre, Carl, circa 1973-1986 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Arman, 1979-1995 (Box 1, Folder 33-34)
  - Arman, 1957-2008; Included are one sound disc (vinyl) and two duplicate sound discs. (Box 2, Folder 1-10)
  - Asger, John, circa 1954-1960s (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Austen, Hatmut, circa 1999-2010 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Aziz, Philip, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Baj, Enrico, 1962-2004 (Box 2, Folder 14-19)
  - Barr, David, 1967-2009 (Box 2, Folder 20-21)
  - Bartlett, Jennifer, 1990s (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Baxter, Iain, 1972-2006 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Bayer, Herbert, 1956-1996 (Box 2, Folder 24-25)
  - Becherer, Joseph A., 1997-2009 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Bochner, Mel, 1973-2007 (Box 2, Folder 27-28)
  - Bourgeau, Jef, 1995-2009 (Box 2, Folder 29-30)
  - Branstner, Holly, 1995-1997 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Christo, 1966-2009 (Box 2, Folder 32-36)
  - Christo, 1970s (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Chryssa, 1963-1976 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Crone, Rainer, 1973-2005 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Degas, Edgar, circa 1958-1959 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Dibbets, Jan, 1970-1990 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Domela, Cesar, 1965-1985 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Dorazio, Piero, 1968-1987 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Flavin, Dan, circa 1967-1973 (Box 3, Folder 8-9)
  - Fontana, Lucio, 1960-2006 (Box 3, Folder 10-13)
  - Frankenthaler, Helen, 1984-1998 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Friedman, Sheila, 1989-1995 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Gelfman, Lynne Golub, 1980-1995 (Box 3, Folder 16-17)
  - Goeritz, Mathias, 1960-1977 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Gorin, Jean, 1965-1983 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Henderson, Shirley, 1989-1995 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Higgins, Dick, circa 1966-1989 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Hill, Anthony, 1968-1990 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Indiana, Robert, circa 1963-1970 (Box 3, Folder 23-26)
  - Jacquet, Alain, 1964-1992 (Box 3, Folder 27-28)
  - Kepes, Gyorgy, circa 1977 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Kidner, Michael, 1983-1990 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Kirili, Alain, circa 1970-1978 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Lemoine, Serge, 1997-2008 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - LeWitt, Sol, circa 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Lichtenstein, Roy, 1989-1997 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Lipchitz, Jacques, circa 1960-1972 (Box 3, Folder 35-39)
  - Mack, Heinz, 1965-1973 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Madelinski, Ron, 1988-1995 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Martin, Kenneth, 1975-1981 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Miralda, Antoni, circa 1970-1992 (Box 4, Folder 3-8)
  - Moholy-Nagy, Laszlo, 1968-2006; 1942 (Box 4, Folder 9-11)
  - Morellet, Francois, 1958-2010 (Box 4, Folder 12-15)
  - Newton, Helmut, circa 1992-2003 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Nonas, Richard, 1976-2001 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - O'Doherty, Brian, 1966-2009 (Box 4, Folder 18-22)
  - Oldenburg, Claes, circa 1966-1971 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Oppenheim, Dennis, circa 1971 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Pepper, Beverly, 1954-1999 (Box 4, Folder 25-30)
  - Picasso, Pablo, 1956-1986 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Piene, Otto, circa 1966-1969 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Pozzi, Lucio, 1974-2006 (Box 5, Folder 1-7)
  - Rauschenberg, Robert, circa 1984 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Raysse, Martial, 1964-1970 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Redstone, Louis, 1963-1998 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Restany, Pierre, 1963-2003 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Rops, Felicien, 1959-1969 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Rosenquist, James, circa 1982-2006 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Rotella, Mimmo, circa 1966-1968 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Sandberg, Willem, 1958-1995 (Box 5, Folder 15-16)
  - Schapiro, Meyer, 1955-1996 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Schneemann, Carolee, 1965-2008 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Segal, George, 1963-1980; 2002-2004 (Box 5, Folder 19-21)
  - Snowden, Gilda, 1989-2006 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Spoerri, Daniel, 1962-1994 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Stankiewicz, Richard, 1963-1997 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Steiner, Ralph, 1975-1986 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Strand, Jon, 1996-2006 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Szeemann, Harald, 1966-2005 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Trova, Ernest, 1965-1968 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Uecker, Gunther, 1966-1992 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Van der Marck, Marc, circa 1975-1998 (Box 5, Folder 30-36)
  - Van Hoeydonck, Paul, 1964-2009 (Box 5, Folder 37-38)
  - Varnelis, Kazys, 1970-2005 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Venet, Bernar, 1966-2009 (Box 6, Folder 1-7)
  - Vihos, Georg, 2008 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Vostell, Wolf, 1970s (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Wise, Gillian, 1968-1976 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Wolff-Metternich, Peter, 1985-2007 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Wolfson, Mitchell, 1985-2006 (Box 6, Folder 12-13)
- Museum Administration Records, 1963-2009; Series 3; 1.3 Linear feet Boxes 6-7
  Museum Administration records consist of files kept by Van der Marck to document his tenure as director or curator at various museums. Files may include museum exhibition planning records, acquisition records, administrative records, news clippings, press releases, correspondence, photographs of Van der Marck at various events, and photographs and slides of artwork.
  Arrangement note
  Folders are arranged alphabetically by name of museum. Documents for each museum are maintained in Van der Marck’s original order.
  - Center for the Fine Arts, Miami, 1979-1986 (Box 6, Folder 14-22)
  - Dartmouth College, 1973-2009 (Box 6, Folder 23-28)
  - Detroit Institute of Arts, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 29-31)
  - Detroit Institute of Arts, 1986-1998 (Box 7, Folder 1-9)
  - Henry Gallery, University of Washington, 1986; 1970-1974 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Museum of Contemporary Art Chicago, 1966-2009 (Box 7, Folder 10-18)
  - Walker Art Center, 1963-1967; 1990 (Box 7, Folder 19-21)
- Professional Records, 1958; Series 4; 1.1 Linear feet Boxes 7-8
  Found here are records of Van der Marck’s professional activities outside of his employment as museum director or curator. Included are files on his participation as guest curator of exhibitions, committee participant, and exhibition juror. Also found are lecture files containing invitations, press materials, and drafts of lectures given by Van der Marck. Additionally there are general professional activity files, a few research files, copies of published articles by Van der Marck, records of job offers, and documentation on his role as curator for the Seattle World’s fair. Any of these files may also include related correspondence, planning documents, and photographs of events.
  - Activities, 1967-1981 (Box 7, Folder 22-29)
  - Art Exhibition Juries, 1964-1980 (Box 7, Folder 30-31)
  - Art Exhibition Juries, 1980-1995 (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
  - Articles Written by Jan Van der Marck, 1968-1986 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Aspen Institute, 1993-2004; 1974-1980 (Box 8, Folder 4-6)
  - "Beyond Illustration" Exhibition, circa 1971-1973 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Dennos Museum Center, 2000-2005 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - F. T. D. Advisory, circa 1970-1974 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - "In the Spirit of Fluxus" Exhibition, circa 1988-1995 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Job Offers, 1971-1980 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Lectures, circa 1965-2002 (Box 8, Folder 12-15)
  - Museum of New Art, 2000-2003 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Museum Planning and Research, circa 1958-1974 (Box 8, Folder 17-19)
  - NBC Special Report:"Crisis in Thebes", 1994 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Realist/Naturalist Sculpture, 1985; circa 1972-1973 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Research on "Iconology Dancing Salome", 1958-1979 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Seattle Art Museum (Bagley and Virginia Wright Collection), 1964-1999 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Seattle World's Fair, 1961-1962 (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Unidentified Manuscript, 1958 (Box 8, Folder 25)
- Papers Concerning Bookbinding, circa 1962-2009; Series 5; 1.2 Linear feet Boxes 8-9
  Papers concerning bookbinding document Van der Marck’s research and personal collection of contemporary bookbinding and book arts. Files on bookbinders and book artists whose work he purchased for his own collection may include correspondence, sales records, exhibition records, and photographs. Additionally there are files of slides of bindings, correspondence with libraries and organizations such as the Grolier Club, and records of his donations of these works. Miscellaneous records include correspondence, lists, notes, and printed material on this topic.
  - Bookbinding Labels and Statement From Slusser Gallery Exhibit, circa 1996 (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Contemporary Art Bindings, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Gifts to Koninklijke Bibliotheek, circa 1996-2006 (Box 8, Folder 28-29)
  - Association Internationale de Bibliophile, 1997-2003 (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - Bibliotheque Historique De La Ville De Paris, 1997-2009 (Box 8, Folder 31)
  - Bibliotheque nationale de France, 1990-2006 (Box 8, Folder 32)
  - Claes, Edgard, 2000-2004 (Box 8, Folder 33)
  - Ely, Timothy C., 1985-2006 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Fie, Phillippe, 2004 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Glaister, Donald, 1980-1998 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Grolier Club, 1997-2003 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Hammer, Jonathan, 1991-1997 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Hugnet, Georges, circa 1962-1999 (Box 9, Folder 6-8)
  - Knoderer, Daniel, 1998-2004 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Lecuire, Pierre, 1988-2005 (Box 9, Folder 10-11)
  - Leroux, Georges, circa 1986-2002 (Box 9, Folder 12-13)
  - Library of Congress, circa 1988-1992 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Lobstein, Alain, 1986-2005 (Box 9, Folder 15-16)
  - Mathieu, Monique, 1985-2007 (Box 9, Folder 17-19)
  - Mowery, J. Franklin, 1990-2001 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Peller, Hugo, 1990-1991 (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Richard, Michel, 1997-2005 (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Robinson, Ivor, 1982-2005 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Rousseau, Florent, 1998-2009 (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Taral, Alain, 1990-2009 (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Tarlau, Jill, circa 1997-1999 (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Miscellaneous Records, circa 1985-2009 (Box 9, Folder 27-29)
  - Slides and Color Transparencies of Bindings Donated or Sold, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 9, Folder 30-32)
  - Slides, circa 1990s (Box 9, Folder 33)